- The real trick is making sure,
that both those lines are level.
Mine aren't.
[trimmer buzzing]
Hi guys, my name's Matty Conrad,
and I'm gonna show you the four easy steps,
to take care of your beard at home.
[relaxed music]
Now I know a lot of us are feeling
a little overgrown these days,
because we haven't been able
to go and see our barber,
to take care of our beards.
And grooming your beard can
be a really tricky procedure.
Well, I'm gonna show you
just a few easy ways,
that you can take care of it at home,
that'll get you over the hump.
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Step one is wash your beard.
Now this is a really important step,
because beards gather a lot of bacteria,
collect food and all
sorts of other things.
It's really important,
especially right now,
to keep your beard clean.
So choose a beard cleanser,
that you can use every single day.
Something that's gentle, and something
that is gonna moisturize the skin,
beneath the beard to prevent flakiness.
Now for those of you, that are
quarantining with a partner,
my biggest suggestion is, take a towel,
and lay it down over top of your sink.
This will help you avoid
all those little hairs,
that gather and just
make your partner crazy.
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Step two is detangling.
For this I like to use a wide tooth pick,
because it puts a lot less
tension, on the beard hair.
As you run it through
the beard, you wanna keep
going through, until you
feel no more tension,
and no more pulling of the beard.
Once you've done that all the way through,
you've gotten rid of all the tangles.
And you're ready to move on to step three.
[bright music]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Step three is the interior.
That's the bulk and
the shape of the beard.
For this, we wanna take
our adjustable clipper,
and set it halfway open,
which means you're gonna move
the lever halfway, between
all the way forward,
and all the way back.
Turn it on and take the
clipper upside down,
creating a nice straight
line, working downwards.
Always working downwards with the beard,
will help you preserve length.
If you work upwards,
it's gonna grab the hair,
and you're gonna take chunks.
Working downwards will make it smoother.
Start from the top near the sideburn,
and create a wall straight down the side,
just looking for the hairs,
that are sticking out and flying away.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
You wanna think of this
area, kind of like a wall,
and make this nice, and flat, and smooth.
Once you've taken your first pass,
take a brush, and brush the hair down.
You'll notice as you do this,
other additional hairs pop
out, that you didn't get before,
because they were tangled in the beard.
Do this two or three times,
and repeat the process,
until the side is nice and smooth.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Then you're gonna repeat
this on the other side.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Once you've got the walls
finished on either side,
nice and flat and smooth with no flyaways,
work very slightly underneath the chin,
but be careful in this area.
You don't wanna remove too much hair,
because this is where
the bulk of the beard is.
Brush the hair down slightly, and just take
one single pass over top,
underneath your mouth.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
It looks better already.
The second part of the
interior is called the shelf,
and that's the length
of the beard underneath.
This should have a slight
downward angle forward,
so it looks more like a jaw shape.
What you wanna do, is tilt your head back,
take your clipper inverted,
and punch a straight line,
from the front length of the beard,
right towards your Adam's apple.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Once you've done, a single
pass, take your pick,
and pull down any hairs, that
may be tangled underneath.
[relaxed music]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
And take a second pass to clean it up.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
This area underneath
the neck, will grow hair.
Your goal is to make
sure, that you don't see
any hair growing on the
neck, behind the front line,
or the length of the beard.
If you see hair growing
down here, clean that up.
My suggestion is to
take your clipper first,
reverse it, and work upwards
just softly on the neck,
to take the hair nice and
short, before you shave it.
This'll make it much more comfortable
for you, to remove with a
razor or with a trimmer.
[relaxed music]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Now it's time for step
four, which is the outline.
Now the outline of the
beard is very important,
and it's broken down into three steps.
The top line, the base
line, and the lip line.
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Let's start with the top line.
To create a strong top line,
you're trying to create a nice clean line,
from the corner of the sideburn,
towards the corner of the mouth.
This line can either be straight,
or it can be slightly curved.
Most people wear their
line slightly curved,
but if you have a wider face shape,
I suggest using a straight line.
It'll make you look leaner.
Take your trimmer and
turn it on, invert it,
and punch a line descending
from the corner of the sideburn,
toward the corner of the mouth.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Once, you wanna remove the hairs
that grow up in the cheeks,
turn your clipper over,
and push up away from that line.
This gives your beard the appearance
of being thicker and stronger.
Repeat it on the opposite side.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
The real trick is making sure,
that both those lines are level.
Mine aren't.
[relaxed music]
[clipper buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Much better.
The baseline is the bottom part
of the outline of the beard.
It starts behind the ear, and descends
all the way around the Adam's apple,
and up the other side.
You want this to be as clean
and strong as possible.
Start from behind the
ear, making sure you hold
the bulk of the beard out of the way,
and outline it using your trimmer,
delicately pressing a line in.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Now we have a nice line
from the corner of the jaw,
descending towards the Adam's apple.
It's easiest to just lift your head,
carve in a nice straight
line right at the corner.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
And work your way down
towards the Adam's apple.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Now we're gonna start
on the opposite side.
[relaxed music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Brush through your hair, just to make sure
you got all the pieces,
and that there aren't
any additional flyaways.
[relaxed music]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
The lip line, which is the last step.
You wanna make sure, that your mustache
isn't going over the crest of the mouth.
So to do that, I like to
comb all of the hair forward,
and I like to create something, that peaks
very slightly in the center.
For people that have short beards,
they can follow the top lip line,
creating a soft peak in the
center, using their trimmer,
but for longer beards,
it's better to create
an arcing shape away to the corner.
To do that, turn your clipper on its side.
Start in the center, and roll outwards,
towards the corner of the mouth.
[funk music]
[trimmer buzzing]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
Once you're all finished,
I highly recommend
applying beard oil, to nourish
and moisturize the beard.
To apply a beard oil, just
take two or three drops,
and work it between the
palms of your hands.
Apply it throughout the beard vigorously,
so it gets all the way through,
and coats all of the hair.
To finish it off, and make sure, it gets
all the way through the beard,
use a natural bristle brush.
Natural bristles have a tendency
to move oil around in the hair,
and will actually help
you condition the beard.
[funk music]
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.
And there we have a perfectly
groomed longer beard.
So when it comes to growing out a beard,
let's say you've never had one before,
and you're looking at COVID quarantine,
as your opportunity to go for it.
A couple of steps need to happen.
First of all, you need to stop shaving.
You need to see what's
gonna grow in and how thick.
Some people have very dense
growth all over their face,
and some people have very patchy areas.
That's okay, because not all
beards need to look the same.
There's lots of different types
of beards, that you can pick.
If you have very patchy
cheeks or bald spots,
you may wanna consider
going with something lower,
maybe a goatee, or simply
rocking the mustache,
because I think that's cooler,
than people give it credence to.
But if you are somebody
that's trying a beard out,
and has a full growth all
over, I highly suggest
just focusing on the outline of the beard,
for the first two to three months,
and letting the bulk of the beard grow in.
The only area where you may wanna consider,
trimming it down slightly,
is in the cheek area,
and making sure, the outline
stays nice and crisp,
from the corner of your jaw, to
the top of your Adam's apple.
That's gonna give you
the strongest beard shape,
and give you a fighting chance,
at growing a damn fine looking beard.
Good luck, and good grooming.
CUT, BARBER MUSIC PLAYING.